Hello, welcome. It is November 5th, 2025
and we're in active inference
gueststream 123.1
with Marcelo Guzman learning with
physical networks. So Marcela will give
a presentation and then I will read some
questions from the live chat. So thank
you for joining to you for the
presentation.
All right, thank you Daniel. Thank you
for the invitation. So I'm Russell
Gusman. I'm a postto at University of
Pennsylvania and today I want to talk
about learning with physical networks.
So one such example is the one that
you're seeing to your left in your in
your video. This is an electronic
circuit. Okay. uh seems kind of
complicated but this electronic circuit
has a property that's able to self adapt
and by doing that it can learn machine
learning tasks like a computer like an
artificial neural network. Um the topic
of my talk is going to be centered
around two papers that appear this year.
One is microscopic imprints of learn
solutions in tunable networks. It's open
source in PRX. And the other one is
physical networks become what they learn
which is in physical review letters. And
in a nutshell, what I want to tell you
is how physics shapes the way these
machines learn. All right? And hopefully
by the end of this this talk, you're
going to understand this picture that is
appearing to your right and I'm going to
explain it to you later.
So let's begin with with learning. So
when we think about learning, we have
these two big paradigms right now. We
have this very trendy paradigm of
machine learning. Okay? And on the other
hand, we have our brain or what happens
in biology, what I call biological
learning. And these two paradigms are
very powerful although they are very
very different. Okay? And so here I'm
listing some of the differences that uh
that that are in between these two. For
example, in artificial neural network,
what you usually do is to modify the
weight parameters. Current technologies,
current uh large language models have
around 10 to the 12 parameters.
Everything is digital. Everything is
happen in your computer or uh in data
centers. It's very energy demanding.
Everything is centralized by CPUs or
GPUs and it lives in the virtual world.
There is no physics. Okay. On the other
hand, if you consider the brain,
what you do with learning is you modify
this synaptic strength. You have around
10 to the 14 synapses. Everything is
analog and from time to time you go to
the to the digital domain. You have this
spikes very energy efficient. Okay? So
to operate the brain you just spend as
much power as a light bulb.
is distributed that is you don't have
any uh any CPU or GPU and it's subject
to physical laws.
So but learning is a much broader
phenomenon.
Okay.
And what I want to introduce now is a
third paradigm that we call physical
learning. So these are two these are
this is one example of a physical
learning system. So this is a resistor
network. Okay. So all the edges are
resistors. This is the experimental
realization. And what this resistor
network does is to modify its own
conductances. All right. And there and
therefore by that learning uh machine
learning task. It has around 10 to the
two parameters. This is a very novel
technology. Uh it's completely analog.
It's energy efficient. It's fast. It's
distributed. And what I want to
highlight is that it is also subject to
physical laws. All right? You cannot
circumvent those.
So why do we want to study this kind of
third paradigm? And there are two main
reasons in the community. One reason
which is more on the engineering side is
to improve the current technologies of
machine learning. Can we make artificial
neural networks more energy efficient?
Can we increase the speed? Can we make
it more robust to damage?
But there also the fundamental part of
it and this is uh what uh what I'm
interested in is that maybe by studying
these kind of systems we can understand
some more complex biological phenomena.
These physical learning systems are
simpler than biology and yet they are
complex enough to display learning.
All right.
So let me begin by introducing a
dictionary. So what is what in this
learning physical network? I am going to
take as a starting point an artificial
neural network. Okay. And I'm going to
compare side by side with this learning
resistor network. So the nodes in an
artificial neural network are basically
the neuron activations. In the resistor
networks these are going to be voltage
nodes.
The edges in an artificial neural
network has the weight parameters. In
the resistor network, it's going to
contain the conductances of my edges
and the external inputs are fed as input
data here X in the artificial neural
network. Whereas in the resistant
network, it's going to be fed as input
current.
All right.
So how do we convert inputs to outputs?
That is what is the forward problem or
what is the input to output relation and
what is the inference problem. So in an
artificial neural network what you do is
you take some inputs you multiply them
by a weight matrix W1 for example and
then you apply a nonlinear
transformation let's say a sigma
function and then that result you
multiply it by the next matrix weight
matrix layer u and then you apply a
final nonlinear transformation so that's
why you go from X to Y the output in the
resistor network what you do is you are
going to apply the current. Okay. And
then you're going to let the system do
it its thing. Let physics work. That is
the equilibriation part. So currents are
going to be reaccommodated in the
network etc etc. You wait till it
reaches the steady state and you're
going to select one of the nodes or a
handful of the nodes and you're going to
read out the voltage that you obtain.
And of course the voltage is going to be
a function of the conductances and the
currents.
So notably this is this is where where
the key difference lies. This process of
equiliberation must obey physical laws.
And for example in um in a resistor
network there are two laws. One that is
called the cure current law. That is at
every single node in this network all
the current in must equal the current
out. And also uh for every loop the
voltage across the loop must be zero.
That's circus voltage law. So this is a
physical constraint. No matter how your
circuit is designed, you have to buy
this. Uh so inference in this problem is
defined by physics.
And now we have also the inverse problem
which is basically learning. So what you
do in an artificial neural network is
that you want to update the weights such
that you decrease the cost. And the the
cost is basically a distance between the
output Y and a desired output white hat
Y hat. In learning uh for resistor
networks, you basically update the
conductances K to decrease the distance
between what you obtain as a voltage
output and what your desired voltage
output is. All right.
And this not these networks are built in
lab. So here what I'm showing you is an
experimental learning resistor network
um built by my colleague Samo at UPUP.
Uh here I'm highlighting in red one
resistor. Okay. So this is one adaptive
resistor and each of these resistor is
able to update its conductance value
based on pure local information just
based on the voltages across its
terminals and it learns through a
learning rule called couple learning. So
if you want to know more details about
this experimental circuit, you can check
these two references.
Um just for this presentation I'm going
to show you a video um of a
classification task performed by this
machine. So this is a very simple task
but it's it's helpful for visualization.
Um basically you have two axis here axis
the horizontal and the vertical axis
representing inputs one and two. All
these data points are training data
points and the goal of the of this task
is to place a decision boundary right in
between these two classes of points. The
background color is the prediction of
the network at the very beginning of
training. So it's basically everything
is blue. But as training progresses u
and this is experiments the network is
able to correctly place this decision
boundary in a couple of seconds. Okay.
So these networks work.
Now what we have to understand here is
that physical learning in this system is
a double optimization problem. So let me
explain this. For the forward problem
that is from input to output we have
this process of equilibriation
and let me take the simplest kind of
systems we can consider linear resistors
that is you have to be ohms slope that
is basically the statement that the
current at each edge is basically the
conductance of the edge times the
voltage drop of that edge. So if we
consider that kind of system then
equilibration is basically the
minimization of the electrical power
that is whatever you get as a physical
response minimizes this power and the
electrical power is basically the energy
per unit of time that you are consuming.
So this mathematically is the sum over
all the edges of the conductance times
the voltage drop square
such that the response is basically the
minimizer of the power minus the input
constraint.
Um geometrically you can think about
this power as a physical landscape. All
right as a physical landscape in a very
highdimensional space of voltages. So
here I just put a cartoon at the bottom.
um each axis represents the voltage of
one of the nodes. So for this picture I
have 4x4 nodes that is 16 dimensions and
over this land over this space I'm going
to define the power
and under the physical response the
voltage response is one is going to be
the one that minimizes this this one. So
that's one minimization.
Where is the second minimization? Well
the second minimization is learning
itself. All right. To solve the inverse
problem, you have to update the
conductance to decrease the cost. And so
you can see that learn solutions are the
minima of this cost landscape.
Now notice that this is another
landscape that lives in a completely
different space which is the space of
parameters, the adapt the adaptive
parameters, the space of conductances.
and learning solutions learn solutions
are at the bottom of this
very very well. So let me just zoom out
a little bit. Uh so this is the
fundamental difference between an
artificial neural network that only
minimizes the cost and a learning
resistor network that has to minimize
the cost and the power. And so you may
say well this seems like a more
complicated problem. So instead of one
minimization have to do two
minimizations. Uh but it turns out that
the minimization of power is automatic.
This is just nature doing its own thing.
And I'm going to show you further that
because of this double optimization
problem, we can get some very nice
results and intuition of the inner
workings of learning in this process.
All right. And also let me mention that
this physical learning as a double
optimization is very general. It is
regardless of the architecture you use.
You can use the grid network that um my
colleagues built in the in the lab or
you can use a completely disorder
network. It is independent on the
learning role whether you use gradient
descent stoastic gradient descent couple
learning heavian learning it does not
matter and it is independent of the on
the learning task whether you use
classification regression or you name it
so it's it's a property of this physical
learning systems
so what are the consequences what are
the consequences of this double
optimization problem
and to walk you through this talk I want
to introduce a very simple example which
is learning one data point. So some
people may say oh but this is not
learning this is just fitting one data
point maybe but I think this is going to
be it's going to fix some ideas. It's
going to be very intuitive.
So consider the following. Consider a
disorder resistor network of 300 nodes
like you see in the picture and roughly
700 edges and consider the following
task. Imagine that I input current I
such that at these nodes blue and red
the voltage is going to be fixed at zero
and one.
And the goal of this is and the goal of
the task is that very far away at these
two nodes I would like to have a precise
voltage value of 099 and 001.
All right. So let's say we begin with
all the conductances being equal to one.
So here the conductances are colored uh
here the edges are colored according to
the conductance value. You can see that
they are all one. You apply the input
current. You let the system accelerate
and what happens is that the voltage
response is going to minimize the power.
All right. So here what you're what
you're seeing is the voltage value. All
right. The voltage value of every single
node in the background as the response
of the system. You can see that where I
input zero and where I input one, I have
blue and red. But as you go far away
from these two nodes, it everything goes
like in between to the gray area in
which the voltage is 0.5.
Let me give you a little bit of more
detail to the forward problem. So I told
you that the power is the sum of over
the edges of the conductance times the
voltage drop. Mathematically speaking,
you can always write this down as a
vector of voltages times a matrix H
times the vector of voltages if it's a
quadratic form.
And this matrix H is what we know as the
physical hessen. All right, that's a
good hess. It's just the second
derivative of the power with respect to
the voltages. And this is where all the
conductances get into play.
So this H matrix depends on two matrices
delta and K. K is a diagonal matrix of
all the conductances and delta it is
known in network u u literature as the
incidence matrix. So it's basically
telling you the connectivity of your
network. It is going to be one if an
edge is connected to a node if it is
incoming minus one if it is outgoing and
zero if it is not connected.
So, so the power can be written in terms
of the hess of the physical hash and
therefore the response of the system it
is in is it is it can be written in
terms of the physical h it is the
inverse of the physical hession times
the input current. So that's exactly how
you get the voltage response of the
system and then once you get the voltage
response you measure
at these two nodes of interest and you
see what you obtain. So here this
measurement I put it in terms of a
projector meaning that out of all the
voltages that I obtain from my response
I will only project into the two
voltages of interest two nodes of
interest and what you get according to
this to this uh color bar scale is that
everything is roughly 050.
All right but this is not what what we
wanted. What we wanted was like a
voltage output very precise of 0.99 and
0.01. So what you have to do is to
modify all the conductances to begin
with. All right. Um so I'm not going to
consider a specific learning rule but
I'm going to show you one possible
result uh solution to this problem. In
particular obtain this result by using
couple learning on simulations. But this
is a possible uh solution which is kind
of interesting. So you can see that to
the left the network developed a crack a
line of very very low conductances as
you can see by the color. This line is
basically separating the system into two
sides.
One side that remains with very high
voltage in the voltage response in red.
the other side with very low voltage and
the in such a way that the output nodes
are just on one side of the other of
this crack and therefore achieving this
function.
All right.
So at the end of training whether for
this task or another task what happens
is that you are at the minima of two
different landscapes in two different
spaces.
minimum of the power, one minimum of the
power, one minimum in the cost.
So what can we learn about these two
these two minimum and what I want to do
now is to give you some geometric
intuition of these highdimensional
landscapes.
So first a geometric picture of the cost
landscape around the minimum.
So imagine you're at a minimum of the
cost. Okay. Now what I can do is to
tailor expand this cost. Uh the the zero
term is going to be a constant which is
the the cost that you obtain at that
minimum.
The first order contribution is going to
be the gradient. But since we are at the
minimum that gradient is zero and
therefore the next non-negligible
contribution comes for from this second
order term which is K minus the solution
K times a matrix H which is also a
hessen. although a different h times k
minus k solution.
And this caligraphic h is what we call
the cost h that is the second derivative
of the cost with respect to the
parameters evaluated at the solution.
And since we are at the minimum this is
a symmetric and positive semi-definite
matrix and it has a very nice geometric
geometric interpretation.
The igen values of this matrix are the
curvatures in this highdimensional
landscapes along directions defined by
the IG vectors. So let's take the the
previous example.
So we found this learning solution.
Let's compute the cost hash spectrum
evaluated as the solution.
And what we find is the following. So
here what you're seeing are all the
values
are all the values. You have as many
values as edges in your network. So
around 700. Uh this is a log scale. And
you can see that out of the 700 values
are extremely close to zero are very
very small. So what that means is that
you are in this very high dimensional
space and in 699 directions the
landscape looks flat
and there is one direction there is one
value that is way larger than the next
value by seven order of magnitudes that
is in this high dimensional space there
is one direction in which the curvature
is just huge it's gigantic all right
meaning if you take if you move along
this direction. You can think about this
as the great canyon rim to rim. You take
a step into this direction and you climb
up the cost by a lot.
All right.
By the way, this phenomenon is also
observed in deep learning. So this is a
property of learning in general. Okay,
you have a few stiff igen modes. So what
is this direction? What is the direction
in which the curvature is extremely
huge?
That's what we call the stiffen vector.
the SIF cos vector. So remember that um
this steep vector lives in conductance
space. So I can assign each entry of
this vector to its corresponding edge.
And here I'm plotting the IG vector over
the graph. You can see that most of the
entries are zero or yellow except for
this crack.
Along this crack, the entries are huge.
meaning that if you perturve any of
these edges in black, you're going to
basically climb up the cost and you're
going to destroy the function. And this
is a very sensitive, it makes total
sense because if you look at the
solution itself, the solution is a crack
of low conductances. If you were to
increase any conductance along this
crack, you're basically going to short
circuit your network or you're going to
lose the function.
So
um the take-h home message here is that
the large entries of these stiff cost
agent vectors are the key components for
your learn solution.
And what we did with uh with my
colleagues was to basically relate
the geometry of this co cost landscape
to the geometry of the physical
landscape.
So we observe the following. So I told
you that the cost hash describes the
curvature around the learn minimum in
conductance space. In the same sense the
physical hash describes the curvature of
the physical landscape the power in
voltage space. And what we observe is
that the stiff coing vector the
direction in which the curvature is the
largest
matches very well the soft physical
vector. that is the direction of my
physical landscape in which the
curvature along which the curvature is
the smallest. All right. So you can see
that here this crack in which the edges
are in black are basically the line
separating the red from the blue region.
Not only that, but we run more over
2,000 uh simulations of different
networks with different initial
conditions. And when we plot the cost
value, the stiff cost value with the
softest physical value, we have this
neat power law power to the minus 4.
And so this was a first suggestion. And
and and this first suggestion was that
it is possible to know the function from
pure physical information. That is you
hand them you handle me a network I can
measure the hessen. This is a physical
property of the network which is
regardless of training data regardless
of a task I can measure the hess and by
measuring the hessen the physical hessen
I get information about the cost
landscape about what it was trained for.
So
uh and so and and we get we got very
excited and we call this paper physical
networks become what they learn because
at the end of the day you train the
network and everything gets imprinted
into the physical landscape and we can
measure that physical landscape. So
these are uh just a few properties that
I'm highlighting here. We also studied
the dynamics of learning but I'm not
going to touch on on that subject today
but all right let's let's continue
so we had this relation sorry we had
this relation between stiff cosign
vectors soft physical vectors uh but it
turns out that the relation is much more
complex when you have more than one data
point okay so everything uh I showed you
was for specific example of one data
But learning is about more data, right?
And we realize that stiff cost vectors
are not simply the soft physical vector,
but there is still a relation. Uh
just to give you a simple example
[clears throat] uh in which the relation
is more complicated. Consider this
network here. You have two sources in
red, two inputs in red and two outputs
in blue. And this network was trained to
perform a linear regression. That is I
want the voltages at the output to be a
linear function of my voltages at the
input with precise very precise
coefficients. Okay. So the network will
train in silico and it found a solution.
And for these cases for example the
simple relation between stiffing vectors
and softening vectors does not hold
anymore. You can also consider more more
complicated tasks in which you have to
classify data into three classes. Um and
so these are two examples of systems uh
which are more complicated and we needed
to understand
and so we have to dig deeper and this is
the context of the second paper
microscopic imprints of learn solutions
in tunable networks. Um I'm going to
spare you all the tedious math and I'm
going to give you just the the high
level results. Um but at the end of the
day we showed we demonstrated
mathematically and confirmed numerically
uh that for any any
uh double optimization problem physical
learning you have a structure function
we can find a structure function
relations and this is what I mean by
that. We show that the cohesion at the
end of learning deco composes into two
parts. One that's pure training and the
other one that's pure physics to be more
precise. So if I write down the J
component of the cosession
I can write it down as the contraction
of two tensors two high order tensors
tensor L and tensor S. To avoid all the
index notation I'm going to just write
this as four dots in here.
So what is L? L is what we call the
training tensor. All right. So let's
consider I have R data points. The L
tensor is going to be the sum over all
the data points of the projector Q times
the input data I times the projector Q
times the input data I. Um so this funny
symbol here is just an outer product uh
symbol. And you can see that this
doesn't contain any physics. It's just
input data. Okay, this is the
information you train your network on.
And on the other side you have what we
call the tuning susceptibility tensor.
This is also a higher order tensor um is
the outer product of the same vector
four times. And this vector is what we
call the susceptibility vector. Here is
where the physical hash appears. the
inverse of the physical h and this again
is only physical information. All right.
So where is the function and where is
the structure? I told you structure
function relation. Well the function is
encoded into the hessen into the cost
hash by this geometric picture and the
structure is encoded into the tuning
susceptibility. This is all the
information of the network the
connectivity and the conductances.
You can even go
you can even go sorry to a deeper level
and show the same relation not only at
the level of the hessions but at the
level of the stiff cost I vectors. So
you can show that the stiff directions
that I show you in these landscapes can
be written down in terms of this
susceptibility the normal susceptibility
and the unit vector susceptibility. And
this matrix A is basically what contains
the learning information would be the
analog of the matrix L in here. So next
question is well what is this
susceptibility and how much information
it contains about the function.
So I told you susceptibility is the
outer product of the same vector four
times. uh you can see it four times that
means that the physical hian inverse
appears four times and that's basically
what I explained in the previous
observation that the scaling relation is
power to the minus 4
the susceptibility is also a physical
observable it's a physical property in
fact SI alpha that is the alpha entry of
SI is the voltage of ati due to a unit
current at node alpha here I'm showing
you one example Here I'm showing you I'm
plotting the susceptibility of this
green edge. So that is the voltage drop
at this green edge when I supply
voltages uh currents I'm sorry at
different node locations. You can see
that near the edge the susceptibility is
large but as you go far away the
susceptibility is very low
and for each edge you can compute its
total susceptibility and you can plot it
in over over the graph and what you see
is this structure emerging. So
uh
so let me let me let me show you what we
can do with this. Uh so consider the 2x
two regression example that I showed you
before. Let me show you the cost
landscape picture.
Before training before everything the
the cost values are just distributed all
over the place. But after training the
co values become degenerate almost all
values are close to zero and in this
case you have four stiffen directions
four stiffen values. These are the four
stiffen vectors. Okay. And what we
obtain from the physical landscape that
is I only measure the susceptibility is
a pattern that resembles a lot the ste
vector. In fact, if you compare them one
to one, here I have four different
colors indicating the four different
vectors. You can see that large
susceptibilities that is edges with
large SI correspond to large to edges
with large entries of Igen vectors. So
the large susceptibilities reveal the
key components. Okay. And this is for
one example, but you can do it for 2x5
regressions. And once again large
susceptibilities correspond to the large
entries. You can do it for
classification tasks. And in all these
cases you observe the same trend. All
right. Now notice that this is not
perfect because I don't have the
complete information. This is what we
can infer by doing physical
measurements.
And then we we also run a lot of
simulations and we observe a lot of
properties. For example, we observe that
in across all our systems, highly
susceptible edges tend to block current.
So here to the left, what you're seeing,
we're looking at is the susceptibility.
So white means low susceptibility. Uh
black means large susceptibility of a
train network. And when you compare
these large u susceptibility edges which
are highlighted in green and you compare
it to the current that it flows through
them you can see that high
susceptibility corresponds to very very
low current. All right. So here to the
right what you're seeing is a vector
field plot. The direction of the arrow
indicates indicates the direction of the
current. The magnitude of the current is
in color from white to black and
precisely in the same regions in the
same green regions you see zero current.
Um we also observed that the
susceptibility is dominated by soft
physical modes. So here in the y-axis
forget this notation in y ais what I'm
plotting is the susceptibility computed
with the first n physical modes over the
susceptibility computed with all the
modes. So you can see that by consider
only a handful of modes I quickly reach
one right meaning that susceptibility is
governed by these soft modes.
Um and so in summary what we have is the
following. We have that learning in
these resistor networks is a double
optimization process. All right
minimization of power and minimization
of cost.
We showed that uh in these two papers
that because of this double optimization
process we have a general structure
function relation. We can measure the
key components from the most susceptible
edges. And that's the picture that you
are seeing here. This error mode is
basically the stiff cost vector. And on
the other side you obtain what you
measure from the tuning susceptibility.
And these are the two head the the two
sides of one coin.
And we have basically a new tool to
study and interpret learn solutions in
physical networks.
Uh
so everything I told you was in the
context of linear resistor networks. But
it turns out that this is way more
general. So in fact this is applicable
to any system with a double
optimization. It is applicable to any
continuum nonlinear system. What we did
at the end of the day was tailor expand
around the minima of two different
landscapes. And one such example are
mechanical networks. So mechanical
networks minimize energy. You have an
elastic network. It has its physical
response minimizes energy or free energy
if you're adding temperature. Um and you
can tune you can tune the network you
can tune the stiffness you can tune the
rest length and you can tune the the
network to do to to perform a desired
behavior. In fact nonlinear nonlinear
elastic networks even though you have
springs can be nonlinear in the energy.
Um here just to give you the translation
of the dictionary the nodes are
displacements the edges contain
stiffness and the extra inputs are the
input forces.
So this is also a kind of system in
which you can apply this formalism of
physical learning
and you can even go beyond what is
actually considered learning. So u
consider for example protein alustry. So
I want to show you that protein alaster
can be seen as a double optimization
process. So what is protein alaster?
Consider consider a protein here in
green. A regulatory molecule comes to
bind to the protein. That binding
induces a long range deformation that
then allows a lian to an extra molecule
to couple to it. All right. So in order
for this uh confirmation h
confirmational deformation to be useful
you need to have the right set of
parameters. This is a very precise
deformation and evolution on say uh has
minimized the error has maximized the
fitness in terms of these parameters.
Now the parameters can be the sequence
of amino acids or or the DNA sequence.
So this is one optimization problem just
evolution but physics
obliges you to minimize the free energy
as a function of the informations. So
once again double optimization and it
turns out that proteins are studied as
elastic network models today. So the
question is can the susceptibility
predict the most important amino acids
for alo steady the most important
parameters and this is a problem that I
would say uh in a more canonical sense
it's not considered learning but it
turns on that you can frame it as a
learning problem. All right. Uh so this
is my last slide. Let's zoom out a
little bit. Everything I told you was
about physical constraints. Everything I
told you was came from the fact that
these systems minimize minimize power or
energy in addition to minimizing the
cost. Uh this is only one type of
physical constraint. There are many many
others. For example, when you actually
build the systems, these are analog
systems. You try to build the system,
you try to build it as neat and cleanly
as possible, but inevitably you have
imperfect components. That's a reality
of our physical physical world. You have
imperfect components. It turns out that
when you learn with these imperfect
components, you get some very
interesting behavior. We get that our
learning rules are being modified. Uh if
you want to know more about this uh we
have this archive paper on understanding
and embracing imperfection in physical
learning networks in which we show how
these physical imperfections like um
unexpected bias can impact the learning
dynamics of these systems.
When you have power and energy
minimization and you couple that with
noise and nonlinearities, you can
actually deise out of electric circuits
restricted B machines of very similar
behavior as the restrict machines and
with that you can have unsupervised and
probabilistic learning with contrastive
local learning networks. So that's the
name of these networks contrastive local
learning networks. Uh you can also check
that out in the on the archive. And also
another property of real systems is that
they have limited sensitivity. That is
they cannot respond to any tiny minute
gradient. All right. It turns out that
if you apply if if you consider this
ingredient to these physical networks
that in addition take space take real
space. This limited sensitivity can be
beneficial and can avoid can help
overcome what's known in the literature
as catastrophic forgetting. This is soon
uh going to be on the archive so stay
tuned. Um and with that let me thank you
my collaborators uh that took part on
these two papers Philipe Martins um Nis
VJ Balis Braman and Andre uh who is in
the chat now and also thank my funding
sources um and let me take any questions
you may have. Thank you.
>> Awesome. Thank you. People can write any
questions in the live chat. Andrea,
would you like to give any any comments
or any
questions?
Well, uh, maybe just to say I mean
Marcelo, I'm sorry I had to miss the
beginning because I was teaching, but
um,
>> and probably Marcelo made this point,
but I think it can't be made strongly
enough that, um, you know, uh, when when
you use physical networks to learn
things, of course, there are
disadvantages compared to neural
networks on the computer, but they're
also really significant advantages.
um you know you know and in addition to
practical advantages for example a lower
energy consumption and stuff like that I
think um the there's a huge advantage in
terms of our ability to understand
the nature of the solutions
um
>> and and this because we have this double
optimization process and we can just
look at the physical aspects and they
tell us so much. It gives us a a really
nice handle into how the system is
learning things, the kind of solutions
the system learns.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> Cool. All right. I will read some
questions from the live chat and some
questions that I wrote down. So, first
question from Bert.
Very clear presentation question. How do
you experimentally measure the
susceptibility in a real electrical
network?
>> Oh yeah.
Uh
let me go back
here.
So let's say you want to measure the
susceptibility of the green edge here.
What you basically want want to do is to
apply a unit current at a given node and
you will and by measuring the voltage
drop
of the green edge due to the unit
current at this voltage node you are
going to measure the susceptibility
that's a physical interpretation and so
and so so
yes so here what I'm plotting
are several measurements. So for each
node I'm plotting the voltage drop of
the green edge due to a unit current
there. So here I'm representing as many
measurements as number of nodes. So
that's one way of measuring. Then
there's the second way of measuring
which is by adding some noise to the
system and just measuring the the
the behavior of your your noisy
dynamics. From that you can also infer
the information of the susceptibility
and maybe that's a more more like a uh
meaningful way of measuring instead of
doing one by one because then you have
to do it for every single edge one by
one. Uh
but that that's basically it. is a
measure of voltage drop due to unit
currents at different nodes.
>> Why does the inverse hessen appear four
times?
>> Uh yeah,
this is this has to do with the
mathematical derivation. Uh
um
let me see if I can find uh
Oh yes. So well if it's is part of the
mathematical formulation. So basically
this here's the thing.
Uh let me go
here.
Okay.
This is the I want you to f Can you see
my mouse? Yes. Okay. Here uh you can see
that the physical response is the
physical hash inverse times the input
current. So that's one physical edge.
Now how do you measure the error?
Uh the error usually
is the response minus what you want
squared.
Okay.
So when you measure the the gradient
uh what you will have to take the
derivative of this quantity with respect
to k that is the derivative of the
inverse of the physical hession. But
when you take the hess the cos hessian
what will appear is the derivative of
the inverse of the physical hess to the
power of two.
Turns out that the derivative of the
physical the inverse of the physical h
is basically the physical h multiplies
twice. And so when when you do all the
math you will realize that naturally the
physical hian inverse is going to appear
four times.
Okay.
And by the way, uh I think I I didn't
argue why we call it susceptibility. All
right. And we call it susceptibility for
a very important reason. Uh is because
uh the quantity here is
I I wrote basically the final expression
of this mathematical derivation. But the
initial expression of this mathematical
derivation is that S is basically the
derivative of the physical hash with
respect to the conductances.
And basically what is telling you that
this is measuring how much your response
is going to change when you change a
little bit the conductances. So it's
literally a notion of susceptibility.
How susceptible is your response when
you tweak certain conductances. And it
turns out that the end result of that is
this four vectors that appear in here.
>> Thank you. That's
>> I think it's maybe it's a little bit
easier to understand not why there are
four powers but why stiff modes of the
cos hession are related to soft modes of
the physical hessen.
Right. If you
[clears throat] if you go back to Yeah.
Exactly. Yeah. You want to explain that
Marcel?
>> Uh, sure.
>> That picture is
>> uh Yeah.
So I guess what what you have in mind is
uh that the softest modes are the
easiest to excite.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> Yeah. Exactly. All right. So um so we
found this stiff cost vector in the cost
landscape. All right. In this very high
dimensional cost landscape. These are
the most important parameters. And so
what's the meaning of this soft physical
vectors? Turns out that your physical
response you can decompose it as a
linear combination of all the physical
vectors.
All right? And the magnitude of the
value indicates how easy is to activate
those vectors. And basically what this
is telling me is that the network
learned by virtue of the easiest to
activate mode.
So it didn't it didn't uh it doesn't
have to activate the last mode which is
the most energetic one. It doesn't has
to activate the next one or the next
one. It just simply activates the
easiest mode, the one with the softest
or the smallest physical in value. And
that's how these networks learn. They
learn by softening. By softening in the
right ways, by becoming basically what
they actually learn.
>> Very cool.
Yeah. Like a physical object shaking,
the softest thing is going to start
vibrating first
>> or the the the weakest link in the chain
is going to break. Otherwise, it would
have been a different chain. Uh,
>> and then it's the stiff cough and and
these visualizations make it really
clear, though there's clearly a lot of
math with it, too, that that uh stiff
cost is in the gap between the two soft
parts. So, it's kind of like a a cake
that got um with with a a cut or with a
hard chocolate or something like
separating two parts that have different
resonant modes
>> and then protein makes it makes it clear
as well like if a lian bound in an amino
acid didn't move that non movement
couldn't be a difference for making a
difference for alostary
>> because it wouldn't be responsive. of
where something that's that binds to low
concent or you know moves a lot with
another liant
binding
it's going to start like a rising tide
with the susceptibilities in a ranked
way depending on the the modulator.
>> Yeah. and and and this is yeah that
you're you're correct but and this is
surprising this is surprising because
this is
there are many many solutions there are
many configurations that could lead to
solving this problem this is only one of
them and what we find is that through
these learning rules okay we seem to
systematically find this kind of
solutions in which you soften you
actually work by the softest mode uh and
that's fascinating, but doesn't have to
be the case, right? Uh you could you
could make a contrived example in which
you function because of the hardest mode
of your physical h but that does not
appear in any case and and
but what's beautiful also is that no
matter how it works, this relation
holds. No, no matter whether you work by
your soft mode which is why what we
actually observe or you work by by a
very contrived way of working this
relation stays the same. This is a very
general uh mathematical framework for
this double optimization problems.
>> Okay, thank you. Lot of lot of other
questions. I'll read one from live chat.
So Tucker wrote, "Will science build
effective proteomic computers using
alossteric input output?"
Or maybe a kind of more general variant
of that that I think arises and you
touch upon is what kinds of
computational or cognitive systems could
be designed with a better grasp of what
you're researching.
That's a
a very speculative question. I I don't
know how to answer that. Uh I I think
the value of this kind of research is
that we can actually understand how they
work, how they learn, what the what type
of solutions we're getting at. I I I
don't know yet where this uh could lead
us. I mean that's why we are doing
research in the first place.
Andrea, I don't know if you want to add
something to uh to this question.
>> Um
uh just to say that probably not for
proteins because they're just not big
enough to be highly overparameterized to
do really complex tasks. So the number
of tunable parameters that you have in a
protein, well, you have a choice of 20
amino acids at each site in the
sequence.
So it's determined by the length of the
protein.
And this is why proteins can be
multifunctional. They can have more than
one function, but they tend not to have
more than that most of them have
basically one and some some have a few.
You know, they're just not very many
that that can solve very complex tasks.
So I think the answer for proteins is
really no because they also have to fold
into their structure. um [clears throat]
um you know for the circuits [snorts]
um can these ideas help us make better
circuits? Yeah, I I think so because um
because one of the things it says is
that okay, well, if you have an
imperfect imperfect circuit,
you don't want to tend to have very many
high susceptibility edges where it
really depends on that edge doing the
right thing.
And so, you know, low susceptibility
solutions might be more robust and um to
these sorts of imperfections. And so
then this gives a way of perhaps
training for lower susceptibility
solutions.
Mhm.
>> A as a biologist, that's really
fascinating about enzymes because they
have many constraints that they function
and evolve under many many cellular
constraints and protein production kinds
that that aren't necessarily related to
their enzyatic function. And they do
have they do have a lot of alossteric
and and all those kinds of incredible
structural events.
However, those are like many fingers on
the scale of usually
several but kind of a core activity
even if it's a transcription factor
activity or or some epig genomic
>> functionality that still can have very
complex causal role. But it comes down
to kind of like a a train on a track
accelerating or decelerating or
increasing or decreasing within kind of
one constrained mode of action which may
be a solution to the evolvability.
So then that leads me to to ask like the
physical device you were simulating the
what what are the like the kind of RAM
CPU GPU
analogies
like does different or improved
functionality in the regression task
come from more nodes?
Is it important to build those systems
to have mo different connectivity
patterns
or like what what physical parameters
relate to their ability to perform that
regression
or how large of a regression could the
object that you were working with do?
[clears throat]
>> Yeah. All right. That's a very good
question. I mean there are several
aspects to this question like the
question of the architecture for
example. What is the best architecture
for the circuits? Uh I showed you that
uh
I show you this picture of the square
grid which is basically what we what my
colleague built in the in the lab. Uh
then I worked out the example of a
disorder network. Short answer is that
in general like for the most general
case the I don't think there is a clear
understanding of what the best
architecture should be and it's the same
problem in artificial neural networks.
All right. Um
>> well actually for
>> that being said for simple for simple
networks like linear resistant networks
the ones that we have actually uh
discussed today there is the best
architecture and the best architecture
turns out to be a crossbar array that is
all the inputs connected to all the
outputs that's it with all all wires
that's the best you can do in a linear
resistive network and and that's al
that's that's maybe that's a starting
point to start understanding what the
best architecture of R. Um
uh also we have some general properties
uh that we share with artificial neural
networks meaning that the more
parameters that you have when you are
nonlinear the better you are at
learning. Okay, that gives you
expressivity. If you can tune if you can
just tune more knobs that's better but
also comes at a price and the price you
have to pay well your system is larger
learning takes longer. you have to uh
spend more energy. So there are these
series of trade-offs uh that we have in
these physical learning systems um
uh
and that we are currently investigating.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Very interesting. It reminds me of
the the physical and thermal energetic
or other other sources of energy. It's
striking that they have that formal
relationship to artificial neural
networks that you just mentioned. Having
a more par if compute were free, having
more parameters
barring secondary issues learns better
or or at least on in certain ways. But
then as soon as you start taking
different constraints into effect then
that's why there is no best model size
just even evidenced narrowly by the
different numbers of parameters in
generative AI families because they kind
of cover that spectrum allowing you to
say if you have this much compute you
need this done at this speed this is the
computing cost whereas if you have a
a wired ed up physical system. It's
using the the constraints of or just the
unfolding of physical systems
it in this kind of like free compute
mode.
>> So do they take longer to equilibrate or
is it just get into questions of like
having a a laboratory or that can
measure it or
>> No, no, no. I think I think if anything
the advantage of having this physical
systems is that equilibriates like this.
This is an electronic circuit. It is
extremely fast. I think um what is uh
what is a pity is that for us the
theorists it's extremely hard to to
model when this circuit gets a little
bit more complicated. So but it's just a
I think it's a complication for us
people doing research on on this on
these systems. But the act of physical
system equilibriates very quickly. It's
it's very very fast and very energy
efficient when you compare it to to a to
a computer for example. There's one
point that I
I didn't discuss much which is the topic
of learning roles because everything I
told you is was regardless of learning
role. But the main advantage of this uh
of of this kind of object here the
experimental object is that all the
learning rules are local. That is if you
want to update this resistor you only
need to know the state of that resistor
and nothing else. Whereas if you compare
this to gradient and descent on
artificial neural networks, each
parameter, each edge on your artificial
neural network needs to know all the
other states of of edges in your
network. So you have this gathering of
information, okay, that you have to
gather at the CPU level and then do the
computations and then transfer back to
all the edges. That costs a lot of
energy. But here everything is
decentralized. distributed network and
that's a lot of saving even when you
scale when you scale up.
>> Yeah, a few a few comments on that. That
is sometimes a point that the biomimetic
or neuromorphic
computing communities also discuss or
like the NGCLARN
biological learning package of professor
Aorbia and then also this is more on the
computational side. It's something that
software packages like RX infer or
ultimately just like the graphical
models that we're exploring in active
inference where there can be node local
computation
of local message passing and update
rules
and that constraint or having a
procedure that can be locally performed
kind of
prevents the need for the moving around
of information
that uh abstract kind of touring
vonoman.
>> Yep. like server farm with infinite
resources metaphor like turning tape
with infinite space metaphor kind of has
and then and then another I think really
striking point to explore is that when
it um well first you mentioned free
energy so maybe you could give a comment
on that but the
way that planning works in active
inference agents in discrete or in
continuous time and in discrete time
it's sort of a chess algorithm like
research with with secondary branching
or secondary evaluations, but kind of
like deep policy search uh in that
machine learning uh tradition. But then
in the continuous time planning setting,
it's a tailor expansion. And so then
that allows for these different
generalized coordinates, different
orders or or degrees of expansion of a
tailaylor approximation.
And then that connects to like
hierarchical basian modeling with a
tailaylor series expansion.
So maybe could you make any other points
on the tailaylor series or the free
energy and the temperature?
>> Uh sure. Yeah.
>> Just to just a quick comment basically
on your thing about the vonoyman
bottleneck.
Um yeah so people talk about inmemory
compute and our systems are definitely
that because the memory is in the
resistances in the state of the tunable
resistors
um which is where the computation is
done that right um and but this is also
because they're selftuning
um by the local rule um it's also
inmemory learning
Okay.
>> The tuning is occurring on exactly the
objects that are carrying the memory
which is the tunable resistors.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Okay. Sorry, go back to that.
>> Yeah. Um
so, [clears throat]
so a comment on on the tailor expansion.
Yes. So, uh so the talk I explicitly use
linear resistor networks. doesn't have
to be the case uh just for simplicity
but basically what you want are two
landscapes I mean that's that's the
general description of physical of
physical of these physical learning
systems and around the minimum of these
two landscapes you perform this tailor
expansion all right and what we are
connecting is this second order
description of these two landscapes in
different spaces the co hashion and the
physical h Now during this talk I use
power as the physical landscape. It
doesn't have to be power. It could be
energy and it could be free energy. All
right. Uh you have has to be a or it can
be any leap of function to be to be
fair. All right. So you have a system
that minimizes a leapon function a
physical by its own physical dynamics
and then you want in addition to tune
the parameters such that you minimize a
cost. you have that set up and then you
can apply all of this reasoning. All
right. And the only the and that's those
are the only conditions
two landscapes you minimize or maximize
what these landscapes. Um and you want
your system to be continuous meaning
that the parameters and the to have this
description. the parameters and the
physical degrees of freedom like the
voltages or the positions of your bits
have to be continuous and as soon as you
have that you have all these results
>> for free well for free
you have to do some math but
>> but that's it
>> thank you I'll ask another question from
live chat Bert wrote in mobility
corridors and barri barriers are varied
for example a navigable river by boat or
car Could you capture something like
travel modes?
>> Can you repeat the question? Sorry.
>> In mobility
like in in a civic engineering or just
physical mobility, corridors and
barriers are varied. For example, a
navigable river by boat or car. The
river is navigable by the boat, not by
car.
>> Could you capture something like travel
modes?
I I think that we could capture we can
capture with this formalism these travel
modes uh for these systems these are
station stationary systems that reach
steady state uh that's a fixed point
okay but we are currently investigating
the case in which the steady state the
response is not a fixed void but could
be a limit cycle so the system in time
the response in time is changing and if
you do that we Think that if you if you
do this tailor approximation of the leap
of function that you are actually
minimizing
then you will obtain the same kind of
behavior in which you link the
properties of the co and the properties
of the hession of this leopon function.
Thank you for that comment. It reminds
me a lot of the leopon exponents role in
chaotic systems and complex systems.
and determining divergences. It's it's
again a similar
nexus with like a laminer flow and then
what are the disturbabilities
and then I is that steady state
just one static
approximation
or does that steady state have these
limit cycle or other kinds of chaotic
properties?
I I think so for for the circuits in in
in question we I I don't think we have
observed chaotic properties. I think
what we can do are fix points or limit
cycles.
>> Well, we can tune now more general
behaviors.
>> Okay. Yeah, we could tune to I mean we
can use local rules now to tune limit
cycles or or whatever kind of dynamical
behavior you want to build in.
Um and the nice thing is that these
ideas can be generalized. This you know
this what Marcelo talked about was all
for reciprocal interactions but um the
ideas can be generalized for
non-rescrocal interactions too.
So maybe kind of a a research practical
question like what software or methods
do you use to design those problems and
how do you set out to when you're making
it other than for research explorations
like how would somebody adapt these
methods to a given functionality or
computation
they were thinking of or wanting to
model.
>> Uh so
on the on the experimental side, I don't
think I can talk that much. I think
those ST is building the experiments. I
can tell you on the theory side, we have
I mean if people want to play with this
kind of codes, it's they are fully
available. All right. To simulate the
learning of these physical systems there
there are some GitHub repositories. You
can look at the at the two papers. Uh
uh this open source paper microscopic
imprint of learn solutions in general
networks has a link to the to the to a
public GitHub repository in which you
can play uh
with with this with simulating these
networks. You can train them to do
different things. because you can train
them to recognize images uh do amnest uh
we also have uh let's see a more
powerful
um tool now so this is a project I
didn't have the time to talk about which
is the sec uh the third project
noise and nonlinearities in which we
basically
um endowed this resistor networks this
linear resistor networks with noise and
nonlinearities is and we devised what we
call a restricted curve machine and
these are unsupervised unprobabilistic
models. This these networks that you can
simulate and again you can look at the
paper and you will find the GitHub
repository public um you can simulate
the circuits learning uh unsupervised
tasks learning to to to learning the
distribution that gets from from some
input data. Uh so if people are
interested th those are the things and
at the level of the more engineering
level there are simulations today about
the all the actual circuit components I
think the software is called spice you
can simulate all these kind of uh
learning networks it's kind of it's
smaller than the effective modeling that
we have in our public uh um repositories
but it's also a play where you can
actually simulate this. At the end of
the day, uh there's no black magic in
here. It's just electronic components.
Cool.
Any other comments or anything else you
want to share?
>> Um Andrea, maybe. Well, maybe just um
interest in the biological thing and
somebody asked about proteins. Um
um
uh there's another post talk in my group
um Farid Muhammad Rafier is looking at
um
uh global epistasis in proteins.
So the idea is you know epistasis was
where you do mutation A do mutation B
and if you do both of them what you get
is not the effect on the function is not
the same as if you did them each
separately and then added them together
and in global epistasis these things are
correlated
um globally you know the non-additivity
of the mutations
um and um you know what we think this is
coming from is from being
overparameterized.
And so the nice thing about what the
susceptibility analysis gives you is
that it gives you a way of finding out
what are the key amino acids that are
that you don't want to mess with if you
want to maintain function. Those are the
key edges that Marcelo is talking about.
uh without doing things like deep
mutational scans and stuff like that,
you can get it just from the physical
properties of the protein itself.
>> Mhm.
>> Wow. What's what's very fascinating
about that is I'm thinking about a
protein physical epistasis or alter case
with like vi physics quote physically
transferred vibrational on molecule
modes. Then I'm thinking about other
multiomix data sets like gene expression
and genome variation for like a G-W was.
So both of those
>> we might make networks that have
additivity
like super or sublinear additivity aka
epistasis. So we have statistical
epistasis in quantitative genetics, G-W
was gene expression.
So it just again it's that striking
parallel that there's a similar
susceptibility
framework for thinking about
the abstract
quote non-physical
like a G-W was or a co-expression
network and two LOSI being co-expressed
up and down across tissues. It doesn't
mean that they physically interact or
that changing one changes the other. So
there's all these different networks
and they they and then by overlaying
them it'd be like okay so what
transcript levels
or there could be things that would be
biologically relevant with with the
transcript level could be very sensitive
to phenotype or not and they all kind of
project down to to the biological system
being what it is with the phenotype a as
that kind of
um single register
for all of those statistical
susceptibilities.
So single omic analyses can tell part of
the story,
but then they're only part of the the
susceptibility
and some of that we get revealed by a
single molecule protein. Other other
epistases don't get revealed
at that at that scale.
So it's like it brings a lot of unity to
how those different data sets even the
past ones that were single omic still
have some degrees of variability
reflected
but it was just one experiment so it
didn't pin down every axis of
variability.
>> Mhm.
>> Right. But this is where the
susceptibility analysis could be really
useful.
Mhm. [clears throat]
>> Cool. Any last comments, Marcelo, or
what are your next research
slashphysical steps?
>> Yeah. All right. I Well, I'm very
biased. I always say this, but I find
this topic fascinating because I truly
think that this could be a very tool and
framework to understand more biological
systems. Um I'm my next steps
career-wise I'm moving to the ENS in
Paris. I want to continue doing research
on physical learning also moving a
little bit closer to biological systems.
Uh and just I I think there is a lot of
things to do about how physical
constraints actually shape the learning
of real systems embedded in the real
world unlike un like virtual systems
that in which you're free to do anything
you want. Here we have rules, we have
constraints. How do these constraints
affect the learning of actual physical
systems and biological systems? I think
these are just fundamental questions and
now luckily physicists are just turning
their attention to these kind of
problems. Uh so that's it. I encourage a
lot of people doing this like reading
this kind of of papers and and just
contacting us because I think this is
this is truly fascinating. Awesome.
Andrea, any last comment?
All right, thank you both. Good luck
with your research. Bye.
>> Right.
>> All right. Thank you, Daniel.
>> Yeah,
>> it does, right?
>> [laughter]